<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Todd Levin</title><description>Things that intrigue me</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.7</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 17:28:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Overcoming Imposter Syndrome</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I believe that what my single greatest hurdle in becoming a software engineer is accepting the idea that I can be successful at it.  I started learning to code earlier this year and it was imposing to say the least.  The diverse technologies available to learn combined with how in-depth&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/overcoming-imposter-syndrome/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">fdca5319-cc04-4cbf-ae2a-ab34932f1497</guid><category>Hack Reactor</category><dc:creator>Todd Levin</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 16:47:21 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I believe that what my single greatest hurdle in becoming a software engineer is accepting the idea that I can be successful at it.  I started learning to code earlier this year and it was imposing to say the least.  The diverse technologies available to learn combined with how in-depth and complicated these programming languages appeared to be made starting difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did what most people do when they don’t know where to start, I asked random people on the internet.  I found the site &lt;a href="http://www.quora.com"&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt; which was a wealth of information from people in the industry.  Impressive credentials, with complex, intelligent answers built up my feelings of inadequacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started learning JavaScript with the intention of interviewing with &lt;a href="http://www.hackreactor.com"&gt;Hack Reactor&lt;/a&gt;.  I set upon learning with a passion and improved my skills rapidly.  I began solving more and more complex problems and eventually got accepted by Hack Reactor despite how highly selective they are.  Throughout this process I thought I had no chance and wasn’t good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out there is a concept that is prevalent in software engineering called the ‘&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imposter_syndrome"&gt;Imposter Syndrome&lt;/a&gt;’ which is a belief, despite evidence to the contrary, that success is the result of luck, timing, or the work of others.  The idea that you are a fraud amongst ‘real’ software engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work I have done on the prerequisite studies for Hack Reactor and my interactions with fellow classmates made me aware that the feeling of inadequacy was fairly common.  I continue to have success that I attribute to persistence and a stubborn desire to solve the problem.  One day I hope I can acknowledge that my success is the result of technical skill.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>